Thank you, Lord, for the Spirit of Jesus.
So, for those of you who don't know me, I am the wanderer in Yellowstone who has returned.
My name is Matt. I'm on staff here, one of the pastors.
And the church is gracious enough to me to allow my wife and I to pursue a dream and also to the church.
I'll be here this month, and I'll be bringing most of the messages.
So, I want to start with a question.
How happy would you be if your pastor would be different about the word of God?
Thank you.
What if maybe you didn't really have much of a relationship with Jesus?
Would that be a problem?
What if you weren't concerned that much about gathering and serving with you as a body of believers?
What if the idea that we actually do something outside of fear was kind of, you know, whatever, option?
Not sure what it is. Not sure how to do it.
I mean, I'm describing something that is problematic for you, I'm assuming.
Yes?
Yes.
What if that was true of your other leaders?
Your board members, your children's pastor, your Sunday school teachers, your various other ministers.
What if that be?
I hope that it is problematic to me.
It is problematic to me.
What about if the people who made decisions about how we spend our money, who we hire, who we put in those leadership positions, all of those things,
if for them the Bible was, you know, up those six years.
Now, this thing is, yeah, nice, but the church, you can take it and leave it.
Listen, and, well, we're just here for ourselves.
So, for the next four weeks, we're going to talk about those four things.
The Word, salvation, the church, and listen, ministry, outreach.
It says, we are a church that believes in the priesthood of all believers.
We really believe that responsibility and authority should be wedded,
and so if God's calling you to do something in our midst,
you should have authority to be able to help track and form that.
Not ultimate authority.
It's kind of like, you know, my kids get to decide what they do with their rooms when they were teenagers.
Now, there were a few things they couldn't do with their rooms.
There were some guardrails.
But it's authority and responsibility are appropriately wedded.
And so, quite frankly, the membership process that we're going through are focusing on what are those things that we think are really important to be part of people who get to make those coming good decisions.
Like, we actually think that you should submit to the Bible if you want to be making decisions here, like Candace King and the Church.
We think you should have a relationship with Jesus.
We think the church should matter.
We think mission should matter.
And so, I want to walk that out.
And today, I would like to take these through, but it's difficult to send it to anyone else but me.
And I, so, today, I want to unpack the Word and recognize that the word of God, the longest chapter in the whole Bible,
Psalm 119, which talks so many different ways that we engage with the Word, we believe it, we obey it, that we meditate on it, we sing it, we submit to it,
I mean, I mean, it speaks to us, it changes us, and there's so many aspects that there's no way in one message we can get a comprehensive sense of what God has done
and is going in and through His Word, what His Word is, and the value and importance.
So, I want to take a 30,000-foot flyover, we could do any one of the aspects more deeply, and one of the things that we have designed into
our membership process next week, between 8:30 and 9:30, if you have questions about this message, or there's some videos that we've posted on our website that if you want to cover it with us,
if you want to join the church, you need to view, if you have questions about those, we want to give opportunity for conversation, and I'm asking those, hearing your questions or thoughts, the input,
I mean, so that we can actually be the church together, okay? I hope that makes sense. Okay, so, one of the comments before we get started, I know that, so you hear feedback, and the problem with hearing feedback is, you don't know if the feedback is one really loud person,
or if the feedback represents 10% of the people, or if there are 50 people who have the question, and you just don't know. And so, I try to address things here as much as I can with integrity, but I know that some folks have been concerned about the word covenant,
that we're covenanting together. I think I was the one that saw the last one, I'm really not big into membership, but I'm big into covenanting. So, let me, let me put you at ease.
We're not, we're not saying that we're doing a Noah's covenant, or an Abrahamic covenant. I mean, there's some very clear covenants in the Bible, and we're not on that level, we're not rewriting the Bible, we really are at least committing to it.
But the Bible is full of one and nothing. And so, it's, when we talk about covenants, we're not interested in people joining like a social club. You know, my mom is at the Hershey Country Club,
and she's been a member for a long time, and she said to me the other day, you know, I really don't do much there anymore, and she's not as impressed with the food as she used to be, she can't get out as much as she used to.
She used to say, I don't know that it's worth the money. And so, she's probably not going to be there next year. That's not what we mean, what we thought about number seven.
We're talking about people who say, you know what, I believe the Bible, I'm saved, and I want to partner, I want to put my sword in the towel with people here, and see if we can accomplish something for God.
I think, I think I said last week, it's literally a bit like marriage. It's not called the Spirit's part, but neither does it enter into lightly.
By the way, if you are visiting, I hope that you get something out of the importance of the word, regardless of what you think about community change.
I think as a Christian, knowing about the word is just simply important.
Can we name one for someone? Okay. Awesome. So, we're going to walk through over the next four weeks what our membership covenant is,
and hopefully we'll unpack those four things, and hopefully it's helpful for you.
My door is always open. You can feel free to email me, Matt Lewis, 721 email. Happy to answer your questions.
I'm happy to be taken out for lunch if you'd like. Okay. If you could put the next slide up.
As a member of this church, I accept the Bible as the word of God which reveals the way of salvation and the guide for faith in Christian living.
We want people who say yes to us. We think that that's pretty foundational in the Church of Jesus Christ.
Now, I do realize that what you mean by that, people can mean different things.
And if I can, I'd like to unpack for you what shows up on the Brethren website about the word,
because I think it's actually pretty nuanced, and I think it's fairly well done.
We're not asking the covenant to it, but I think it unpacks things quite well.
So, on their website they say that we center on Jesus Christ as the living word of God.
That's really helpful for me.
It means that when we look at the written word of God, the goal and purpose of the written word of God is to point us most carefully to the supreme revelation of God,
which is Jesus Christ incarnate on us.
Jesus' claim as the supreme revelation of who God is and how we live.
If you want to know what it means to be a Christian, you look at Jesus.
Philip asks this question.
You see, Jesus is near the end of his earthly life, and before his crucifixion, before his resurrection,
and he is taking them in this upper room, John 13 following, and you find this long dissertation,
and it's obvious that the disciples realize that it's different.
Jesus is getting really serious.
It's like my final instructions to the people who are going to lead you to carry out the mission, the ministry, why I brought you all together.
And in that, they have some concerns, because he's talking about leaving.
He's talking about dying.
And they're struggling with that.
And so, in John 14, he says, "Don't let your hearts be troubled."
"Don't let them be troubled."
And in the midst of all of that, Philip finally says, "Well, okay, Jesus, would you just sell us the Father?"
Did you remember Philip or Jesus' response?
"You know me.
Have I been leaking so long, and yet you do not want me."
Now, Jesus is not the Father.
We believe in the Trinity.
God of the Father, God of the Son, God of the Holy Spirit.
There's only one God.
The point that Jesus is making, you want to know what God's like?
Look at me.
I'm the supreme revelation of God.
I'm God in darkness.
He's of inspiration.
How can we be honest in that?
By the way, the whole thing with the Holy Spirit.
Do you know Christians who kind of treat the Holy Spirit as kind of like a healthy person in the Trinity?
Do you say, "If I go, I'll send what?"
A helper.
Or another comforter.
In other words, I'm going to come for them here, and I'm going to go, but I'm going to send another woman.
The third person in the Trinity, the Holy Spirit.
And he's going to come, and he's going to be able to do things in and through you and with you that I need him to do as I go up to the Father.
I also think that the sensuality of Jesus as the living word of God is really helpful when we get to the point of interpreting the word of God.
I mean, a previous church that I pastor at, we used to publish it every month, a Miss Quote of the Month.
It was something that someone said in our church that if you knew them, you understood and made sense, but if you just took it out of context.
And we wouldn't say Quote of the Month.
We call it Miss Quote of the Month.
I remember Ken Castro once said, "You know, you're free in Christ and you can do whatever you want."
And we're welcome in this context, absolutely.
So, when we come to the Scriptures, it's really, really helpful to know that the supreme revelation of God is Jesus Christ, the living Word.
And that our New Testament, our Old Testament, our Scriptures, the divinely inspired and ascertained written word of God, point it.
We're going to say more about that as we continue.
I don't know if any of you have kids that, when you're raising them, they quote you and it's really the Miss Quote of the Week for them.
But God, you said, and they have the words down.
You know, they memorize the words.
I used to tell my kids all the time, "This is what I mean, not what I said."
So, when we look at the Scripture, what God means is Jesus.
He gives you a very clear picture of what He means.
And we, as intelligent adults, can debate the meaning of various Scriptures and how we interpret Scripture with Scripture and how it folds upon itself and how the Old Testament is a shadow and the New Testament is a substance.
We can talk about all of that.
In the history of Christianity, there's always been some clarity around what is essential, what is orthodox, what is non-negotiable.
And then there's not only the dates about a whole bunch of other stuff.
And there's nothing in the dates of grace, but we need to line them up by the person, Jesus Christ.
Okay.
We center on Jesus Christ as the living word of God.
Let's slide.
The Holy Spirit progressively revealed God's one plan of salvation in Christ from the first promise in the Old Testament to its fulfillment in the New.
So, I love this word used here, and I realize the word has taken on new meanings in the United States of America today.
But when it says the Holy Spirit progressively revealed, it means that God only gave them enough that they could begin to incorporate.
Because even Paul says that the law, the Old Testament, the stuff that's the two-thirds of your Bible when you pick it up, that law was, in the King James Version, was a schoolmaster to what?
Lead us to?
Nope.
Who's the second Revelation?
To Christ.
There's a wonderful, sensational piece in that.
The King James Version schoolmaster, and I don't know about you, but I think a schoolmaster is maybe someone who, you know, waxes across the knuckles with a ruler as we step out.
And the papyrus, the 28th Greek, the documents they found, they found this same word that showed up in common language, and it really was translated meaning.
But the law is your meaning to lead you to Christ, and you're no longer under your knuckles.
I absolutely love that, because if you had a nanny, when you were middle, you did what nanny said was.
You said, "Nanny said it!"
But nanny's goal was not for you to listen to nanny when you're in your 40s and 50s and 60s.
Nanny's goal is to incorporate into your very bill to take what's external and internalize a rule of faith, a way of living, a way of behaving.
Right now, it becomes you.
It becomes part of you.
And so, you know, when I cross the road, I look those ways.
The logic of my nanny says, "No, I will serve."
But now, because it's just marked.
And by the way, if you go overseas, don't only look those ways, but make sure which way you're looking first, because cars come from other directions.
Oh, I've just got the right few times.
You know, that little mirror comes by.
Makes you finished.
Okay.
The Holy Spirit progressively revealed, and then here's the next piece.
Oh, one more thing I'm going to reveal.
Jesus, if I told you about earthly things and you don't understand, how do you even understand heavenly things?
Often, I think, we come to the Scriptures and we're looking for them to answer our question in this verse.
And sometimes, they're not actually dealing with our question.
So, you know the story of the eight-year-old boy who came home and said, "Dad, where do I come from?"
And the guy said, "Oh, honey, we'll talk about that a little later," you know?
And he said, "Well, Dad, everyone else in school knows."
He's like, "Eight? I thought I went out of Houston until 12, you know?"
And so, Dad kind of spur of the moment said, "Okay," and went into kind of the child's first sex education.
And when he was dying, he said, "So, does that make sense? Do you understand? Do you have any French foods?"
He said, "I don't really understand, Dad, but Jenny's from Cleveland. Where am I from?"
We often come looking for a certain answer, and the Bible's intending to answer this question.
Because the Bible, when you look at the Old Covenant, it's been aggressively revealed
so that, eventually, we can come to this place where we can understand who Jesus is.
Say yes to Jesus, and learn according to what that means in our life.
The living word of God, and then the written word of God.
This is progressively revealed God's one plan of salvation.
This is another key point.
There is only one plan of salvation.
There's only one.
There's not eight.
There's only one plan of salvation.
Not because we wanted to hear what they had to say.
But we wanted to protect anyone else who was coming to hear what they might have to say.
And their premise was that Jesus actually blew it.
Jesus wasn't supposed to die.
Jesus was supposed to get married, have a perfect family.
And because John the Baptist blew it, it caused Jesus to not be able to finalize.
And so Reverend Sanyang Louie had to come and to fear all the fools.
You do know I don't believe this.
I'm telling you what's wrong.
Just want to make sure.
You know, so a politician might clip that and say this is what the pastor believes, you know.
So they were trying to push this thing that he was going to come and have a perfect family and a perfect kids.
And so the guy was quoting out of John and said,
"So John the Baptist stood up and said, 'Behold the Son of God!'"
And my friend stood up and said, "Excuse me, that's not what it said."
"Well yeah, it is."
"No, it's not."
He said, "Behold the land of God."
Because Jesus was the land slain from the foundation of the world.
There was one from there.
There was not a "oops, didn't work, was kind of a clean."
Before God ever even started this whole process.
He said, "I'm going to want to be in relationship with these people unclean.
I'm getting free will and they're not going to do so with us.
And so I'm going to have to make up for them.
And I can't just overlook my holiness.
I can't just leave the sting under the rug.
Justice must be served.
They're never going to be able to do it."
And so from the very foundation,
"Father, Son, Spirit, Son, you're going to have to go and deal with this."
Son said, "You're with."
And so from the very foundation before God began creation,
you have a clear plan.
And that clear plan includes the incarnation and perfect life
and the crucifixion and the resurrection.
And as Dr. Newell talked to us last week,
the presentation of the blood in the temple and the heavenlies,
that he might come back and redeem us one time.
Okay, next slide.
"Center on Jesus Christ as the living Lord of God,
the Holy Spirit progressively revealed God's one claim of salvation in Christ,
from his first promise in the Old Testament to the fulfillment of the new,
giving in human words and history."
I like that.
You do know that orthodoxy teaches that Jesus was fully God and fully human.
That he's not partially human.
He's not partially God.
He's not sick.
He's 100% God.
And he's 100% human.
He's fully human.
He's fully God.
And Robert Mulholland points out, as well as others prior to him,
that actually that's what the Bible is told.
It's why it's fully human and fully divine.
It is the word of God.
But it's why when you read the Gospel of John and you read the Gospel of Luke,
they're very different.
In fact, if you look at the Greeks, the Greeks are incredibly different.
If you look at Peter, or you look at Paul, or you look at other letters,
you find that, and that's why, by the way, when we interpret the Bible,
we want to look at who wrote it.
Who were they writing to?
What was the purpose for the writing?
Because it informs what God is communicating.
I think it's amazing.
If we were Muslim, we would believe that the crown was just dropped down from heaven.
It's why it can only be in Arabic.
It can't be in any other language.
When you translate it, you lose it.
Because it was dictated.
But we don't believe in it.
The Bible's not dictated.
It was inspired.
Before it came, it was inspired.
God used men and women like you and me to communicate the perfect revelation pointing to the supreme revelation.
Jesus Christ.
Okay.
Next slide.
Given in human words and history, the Scriptures based in Old Testament are the inspired word of God that the Bible says about itself.
And authoritative is what the Bible says about itself.
Forthroity and true in every respect.
Okay.
Continues on the next slide.
The New Testament, witnessing to the climax of that history, is the final rule of faith and life for the church.
There's not going to be a sequel to the Bible.
There's not a volume two after the New Testament.
The canon is finished.
It is set.
We have it.
And it points to Jesus.
It's authoritative.
The New Testament, witnessing to the climax of that history, is the final rule of faith and life for the church.
By the way, here's a nice place to get back to.
When we talk to Scripture with Scripture, we have to understand the intent.
There's a theologian, Feinberg, taught at Trinity, who made the point that when we read the Scripture,
we have to treat the various passages of Scripture almost like it's laid out on a grid of a bulldog.
And we give priority to those passages that most clearly communicate the center of the bulldog.
Which is Jesus.
Let me give you an example.
Paul says to Timothy, "Take a little wine with your water."
I don't think that belongs at the center of other interpretation.
I would suspect that none of you put wine in all of your waters.
Now, if you were traveling missionary in a world where disease was rampant, then adding a little wine as you're traveling,
which was so important to do, actually was like, "Take a little meditation."
If you go on a mission trip, I might say, "Take some box of cycling with you."
So when we read the Bible, when we understand the Bible, we need to realize that it's witnessing to the climax of history,
Jesus Christ coming, and living, and dying, and raising, and eventually remaining to Him.
So for one last piece on what the brethren did, I hope I'm not going too deep for you or boring you.
I just think it's really helpful nuance.
Understanding how we unpack the Bible.
How we understand the Old Testament and the New Testament.
The shadow and the revelation.
Dr. Miller on Saturday last week talked about the Hebrews.
It's all about Christ is a better sacrifice for the Old Testament.
It's a better temple than the Old Testament.
The blood is better.
A better covenant.
All of that because it's closer to the center of that bullseye of who Jesus is,
what He came to do, what He's all about.
Okay.
It's an expression of grateful love to God.
Brethren, believe and obey the Bible.
For only the written word reveals to us Jesus, the living word.
And I think that's very helpful.
Now, I want to add a little bit of something.
I think we do believe, and we do obey the word.
But the group that was going through kind of our mission and vision and then our core values
slash practices, they had a little bit of a practice that I really wanted to.
That we rely on the word of God.
We rely on the living and written word of God.
And I like the word rely because it incorporates believe and obey, but it incorporates more than
that.
Let me show you one more verse because I think this is really, really helpful.
And this is, I'm taking it from the NASD, the New American Standard Bible.
And I'm doing it because it tends to be a more word for word translation.
And so sometimes it's a little word and it's a little harder to read, but it gets at the
actual words.
And in this verse, I think it's a really important distinction.
Because here's what he's saying about the preaching of the words.
Paul writes, "How will they call on him in whom they have not believed?"
He's talking about Jesus.
How are people going to get saved?
How are they going to call on him if they haven't believed in him?
And then, "How will they believe in him?"
And notice what it says here because you're, and I do probably says, "of him."
But here it says, "And how will they believe in him whom they have not heard?"
And how will they fear without a preacher?
You see, the reason I think that the preaching event is so important and that we preach the
word of God and we preach is because it's one of the vehicles that God chooses to speak himself.
Same thing with reading the Bible.
Or, better yet, sometimes meditating on the Bible.
But we can go and we can exegete the Scriptures, we can unpack it, we can try to understand it.
But please realize that the Scriptures have stood the test of time, you and I have not.
And the Scriptures are actually the thing that's exegeting us.
But God is looking to speak to us.
And in this passage, through the preaching event, so please, as I preach, listen for God.
Forget what I say, but listen for God.
Because I often tell people who like to take notes, you know, don't say take notes, take notes.
If God speaks, if God touches your thoughts, touches your mind, touches your soul through the preaching of his word, or the reading of his word, or the singing of his word.
I love when we do a song that's just Scripture.
I don't know what I hear, but I've had moments of worship with songs that are doing the word, "Same who I am."
Because God stepped down out of his word and spoke to me.
Has anyone else had that experience?
And I don't always say, "Boy, if I tell you, you'll forget it tomorrow."
But if God tells you, and that's the gospel.
That's the same.
And so, I want to take a little bit of time and talk not just about the reading of the band,
but also allowing the Scriptures to actually form others.
Okay.
Before I do that, let me give you three things that the Bible is not intended to do.
It's not intended to do display models.
I invited a lady to a Bible study one time.
This was probably 30 years ago.
And she didn't do nothing about Christianity and nothing about the Bible.
But, you know, we had talked a lot, and she was excited to kind of explore it.
And I said, "Do you have a Bible?"
And she said, "Yeah, we do."
And that's the way she does.
Now, I understand that a hundred years ago, family Bibles were critically important because people didn't travel on me.
They were really important, but today they're primarily.
Any of you ever take one of those for Bible study?
And, by the way, I can think the class on the Bible, I understand the goal of the class is to protect it.
But there's something wrong about the device that Christ can teach the Bible to play.
This thing.
So, the Bible is not a display model.
You should be careful.
Second, the Bible is not an idol.
And while I understand the idea of wanting to recognize the authority of the Scripture and holding it up, and I'm not dissing what they're doing, but the temptation is to turn it into an idol.
And I was witnessing in Speaker's Corner in London.
Speaker's Corner in London is a place that's set aside in London where people can get up and talk about anything.
Get up and talk about socialism.
Get up and talk about Christianity.
Get up and talk about this one.
Get up and talk about the economy.
And people gather and they actually debate.
And you'll get two people in lotters who were debating back and forth and people in the crowd listening.
And I worked with a guy who would stand up and he would debate in a morning.
So, there's a Muslim in a morning who would get up and he would teach.
And J. Smith would stand up and he would teach.
And they would debate about the truth of the Quran, the truth of the Bible, who Jesus is according to the Quran, who Jesus is according to the Bible.
And many of us would stand out and shout and get into conversations with people.
And I remember I was in a conversation with this one Muslim guy.
And he was so revering the Quran that I turned and I took my Bible and said, "You know, this Bible speaks to my heart.
It changes me.
It's not the words in the pages."
And I dropped it on ground.
And his buddy was really loose.
He said, "Somehow, I'm a trusty idol."
Now, I'm not going to drop my phone on the ground to show you as an example.
But it's why we can't put the Bible on our phone.
It's why we can't put the Bible on tape and listen to it.
In fact, I would argue that most Christians in most of history wouldn't read their Bible, it was read to them.
Because up until the 1600s in the Gutenberg Press, people didn't read it.
The church might have won, but they were generally read.
That's the reason why people memorized the Bible.
Because they hid it, according to Psalm 119, they hid it where?
In their heart.
They put it within.
Okay.
So, don't make it an display model.
Not an idol.
Next one, it's not a political prop.
This is a picture on May 7th, 2012 of Putin's inauguration.
And I'm sorry, but the Bible is not intended to be a political prop.
Okay, go ahead and pen next.
So, I'd like to talk really quickly about how we then interpret the Bible.
How we intend to understand it, live under it.
And let me begin by saying that the Bible is written in many different genres.
Sometimes the Bible uses a metaphor.
Sometimes it's very liberal.
So, when the Bible says, "Do not commit adultery," it actually means that.
There's no metaphor there.
But there are other places where there are metaphors.
Dr. Walter Martin was an apologist.
He used to deal with various cults, former debate cult folks.
I think he's long gone now.
But he was at a seminar teaching about the difference between Orthodox Christianity and Mormons.
And the difference in their doctrine and why Mormons are not Christians.
They're not Orthodox Christians.
And he'd gotten well known.
And so, for this particular lecture, there were eight leaders of the Mormon Church sitting in the front row.
And he recognized him.
And so, when he came to the time for question and answer, the head bishop there raised his hand.
And Dr. Walter Martin called on him.
And he stood up and he said, "Now, sir, I know you do not believe in the Book of God in the Covene,
or the Book of Mormon, or the Pearl of Great Christ, but you believe the Bible so."
Dr. Walter Martin said, "Sure."
He said, "So, if I can show you in your own Bible that God the Father was at one time a man, will you believe?"
He said, "You can show me that, and I'll become a Mormon tomorrow."
So, he stood and opened the Bible and started to quote about the foot of God doing this.
The hand of God doing this.
The mouth of God doing that.
The finger of God doing this.
What's in, like, fifteen different verses where it talks body parts about God the Father.
He said, "So, you see, Dr. Martin, the Father was at one time a man."
Dr. Martin said, "Can you read one more verse for me, please?"
Sure.
Would you please read Psalm 91, verse 4.
He opened it up and he read, "He shall cover the evening with his feathers under his wings."
He said, "Oh, my God, I'm just kidding."
The point is, if the Bible's even a metaphor, it's meant to be a metaphor.
Um, this is a literal translation depiction of a beautiful woman in the Song of Solomon.
Guys, come to the home and look at your wife and say, "Ah, your nose is like the Tower of Damascus.
Your hair is like a flock of goats."
She will not appreciate it.
You have to understand the cultural coincidence.
Okay, that's not the one that you want.
You know, it's one too.
The problem with doing this kind of stuff is someone's going to remember that and nothing else like them.
I did a sermon one time.
I was talking about, um, how myopic we could become.
That we focus on one thing and we can't see a million around us.
And I was using a morning dove as an example.
Have you ever seen a morning dove walking?
I'm not going to do it because you'll remember only that.
But they put their head out and then they bring their body up.
And they put their head out and they bring their body up.
And they do that because their eyes can't focus in motion.
So they put their eyes out and they focus and all the while they bring their body up.
Well, the first time I saw that I actually demonstrated on the stage.
And 10 years later on Facebook, someone reminded me of my demonstration of the morning dove on stage.
And I said, "Oh, Sonny West Grace, can you remember what I illustrated?"
She said, "No."
So, don't remember that.
Okay.
Let's go to the next slide.
So, we rely on the living and written word.
Let me give you really quickly what the Bible says about itself.
2 Timothy 3:15-17.
Go until the next slide.
April read, 14 following.
I asked her to go back to 15.
She said that's in the middle of the sentence.
Go to the contest and she was right.
I submitted.
So, the Bible in 14 does talk about, you know, it teaches you salvation.
How you get wise to become a Christian.
The Bible's critical.
It's important.
It's wise.
If you're ever sharing Jesus in someone, sharing a testimony by all means.
But at some point, read a verse.
Let's go read the verse.
Because the Bible has a whole lot more power than you and I do.
I mean, the Bible just has this authoritative ability of power to change hearts.
It seems like I am.
Okay.
So, but in 16, it says, "All Scripture is inspired by God and benefits for."
And it says, "For four things: for teaching, for abuse, for correction, and training in righteousness."
So, we go to the next slide and then the next slide.
And what it really deals with is right and wrong believing and right and wrong doing.
The Bible is able to teach us about how we should believe.
About truth.
About how we set our minds on things that are godly.
The Bible is also, next slide, to rebuke wrong beliefs.
But there are groups who believe wrong.
God the Father was never a man.
He went from eternity to eternity.
See, this is what's going to happen.
That's the only thing that Jason's going to remember from my message, right?
I can see it coming.
Next slide.
It's profitable for teaching what to believe, for rebuking what is wrong that we shouldn't believe.
But it also corrects our behavior.
The Scriptures are not just concerned about our cognitive awareness.
In fact, almost always, the pattern in the Scripture is to teach us theology.
And that's the teaching of theology to take us to, therefore, here's how we behave.
Here's what I want you to do.
It's why God chose Jesus as the supreme revelation.
Because, quite frankly, a lot of what Jesus taught is hard to follow.
He did his parables.
And, I mean, he said things that were extreme.
And it's like, "Are you disciples?"
They're like, "Come on, boy.
What do you say?"
And then he's pulling aside and trying to explain again.
Paul makes it simpler for us.
That's why so many people love to live in Paul.
But I would argue, "No, no, no, no.
Look at what Jesus did.
Look at who he was.
Look at how he asked you.
Look at how he treated people.
Look at how he behaved.
Because the Scriptures are all about teaching what's right to believe.
Rebuking what's wrong to believe.
But correcting.
And, by the way, I love this.
On the belief part, it's just a word.
If you're teaching heresy, you need to be calm on that.
Now, I want to be careful.
We talk here a lot about secondary theology.
And it's a longer discussion than we have for today.
But the truth, there are a number of Orthodox things that people, everywhere from the Eastern Church to the Western Church, all across denominations, all across groups, that they acknowledge these simple, basic Orthodox things.
And how we work that out, okay, we can debate that.
Let's not rebuke that.
But if we need the foundation of Orthodox, if one of those talks about the regular freedoms, the rules of faith, it's like, here's the Christian rules of faith, and the Orthodox are over here in Canvas communities up here somewhere.
And that's okay, as long as we don't go outside of these.
And if we go outside of these, we need to be rebuked.
But if we go outside of these in behavior, that's not rebuked.
That's correct.
That's come alongside.
And then, last of all, framing.
When, just like you claim your children, you'll see someone who says, "You know what?
I keep going over and over with my kids, and they're not getting it.
That's pretty close for me."
If any of you quit training for a month and a half, what does your body strength look like?
You know?
It's just training.
Okay.
You get it.
Just real quick.
Let's have a few more slides, and then we'll come, and then next week, about 8:30 to 9:30,
over in the conference room, if there's too many people, we'll go into the youth room.
If you have questions, if you have comments, if you want to arrest me, I don't want to argue with me.
Feel free.
Come.
We'll talk.
I love it.
Okay.
So, one more piece about what the Bible does, and this is not critical for membership here.
You can absolutely disagree with me, but I find it to be very helpful in my own spirituality,
so I want to share it with you.
Robert M. Holland, again, a New Testament professor, and I believe, a great New Testament professor,
by the story, wrote a book shaped by the Word.
And he made a comment, "Academy's love to make these comments that you have to make."
In his first hearing, he goes, "Huh?"
He said, "The Bible is like an icon."
Okay, let me unpack this one.
Go to the next slide.
This is a classic icon, and some of you who were here a year or two years ago will remember this.
It's a classical icon on the phone, and then any art majors here, artists, who can tell me,
"What's wrong with that picture from our perspective?"
Where is the vanishing point?
Do you know what the vanishing point is?
What's that?
Yes, so the table should go this way, but it comes this way.
It's a four-sided table, and the Trinity is at the table, and there's no one here.
And the intention of the icon is to say, "You're here."
And that while you look to God, while you look at God, while you learn of God, while you focus on God,
God's actually looking back at you.
That this is a two-way conversation.
That when we look to God, we, God will take it off.
And if the Scriptures are just like us, we read the Scriptures to learn about the narrative,
to understand how God wants us to live, and behave, and believe, and do.
But the Scriptures are more causal than us.
The Holy Spirit will take the Scriptures and tell them to your heart.
The Scriptures have this way, and it's why I don't just read the Bible once if they haven't read it.
I just don't know how many passages I've gone back to that I haven't read in a year,
and I read it, and all of a sudden, God speaks, and it's brand new,
and I realize how it applies to this part of my life, and I say, "I'm sorry."
Or I say, "Thank you, God."
Or I say, "Whoa, that's good."
I mean, He does all of our kind of things.
And so, too, with the word of God, it can speak to us.
My wife and I were watching this show.
It's one of these reality shows that they're never really reality.
There were teens who were out in the Alaska in the background.
I'm not sure what I mean, but there were four teens.
And whichever teens survives the longest reads.
And it's easy to negotiate.
People can leave and go to the other teens, but if they don't take you, you can't be by yourself.
You have to go to the teens.
And there were this one teen in the Alaska teens, and it's like,
two of them snuck over and stole the sleeping bags of the Delta teens.
You know, like below 30 degrees, how do you live without sleeping bags?
You sort of end up having to, you know, do that.
And this teen that was, I mean, they were just running.
They were mean.
And at the end, there were just two teens, and one of their nasty people, they were being nasty to him.
And so, he decided to lean.
And so, when he left and the other teen was going to take him, they saw this arrow over as a note saying how nasty he is.
And then, they kept showing in images of them talking to the camera about how they've been wrong,
how they've been right, how they've been so good.
And it was so gross that my wife and I were literally sitting on a chair yelling at the TV.
They said, "Who do you want, baby?
It's the way you're behaving now.
You're just going back."
This is so bad.
Literally, we had to watch something else before going to bed.
I couldn't go to bed watching that.
She was absolutely convinced that she was right.
That she had it together.
Anyone in here ever saw him in a tentacle?
So, this next slide shows that Joe Harry Windy, and unless you think that I'm talking about some New Age study,
it was created by two guys named Joseph and Hardy.
I thought I liked that one.
And the premise is that there are some things that is known to you and it's known to others.
It's the face we present.
There are other things that are known to others but not known to you.
She's a great example of that.
She had no clue how beobious and mean she really was.
She was convinced that she was just a saintly person.
And you all know folks like that.
By the way, if you don't know anyone like that, you're probably that person.
Then there's an area that is known itself but it's not known to others.
It's that secret something that we heard there.
And by the way, when you get there, one of the disciplines for that is the discipline of confession.
And you can start by confessing to God but sometimes you find a really good brother or sister to confess it to them.
Because confession can actually bring things.
Confess the first one to another, you may be healed, the Scriptures say.
But then there is this area of your personality in you that drives you in ways...
And it's not obvious to me.
It's not obvious to others.
Economists are not talking about our economy and the unknown unknowns.
According to Ronald Rumsfeld from 20, 10 years ago.
It was in Canada.
There are unknown unknowns.
But I think in our own spirituality, there are unknown unknowns.
And one of the ways that God chooses to get at your unknown unknowns is by you sitting before the word of God.
And letting the word of God exige you.
Letting the Holy Spirit begin depicting the word of God to you.
And its purpose is not so that you can teach someone else.
If all of your devotion time is your friend and prep time, you're going to be a sick puppy.
This is about intimacy between you and God.
And the word of God, the written word of God can point us to the living word of God,
to the inward word of God, the Holy Spirit, in ways you can begin to unravel, unveil things in us
that are excelling, that are hurtful, that, you know, it's Roman 7 now.
What I want to do, I don't do, what I don't want to do.
I find myself feeling evil, deliver me from this wretched body.
Oh, Lord, it's this God intended plan to form you in the name of Jesus.
Why don't you sit before the Word so the Word can get us those places that God knows us.
And God can do this too.
Last slide.
So, as a member of this church, I accept the Bible as the word of God, which is revealed the way of salvation,
the guide to faith, and Christian living.
If you choose to put your folder in the plan with Jesus community over a long time period,
we're going to ask that each way of you.
If you're a visitor, you are welcome.
If you're just an attendee, you are welcome.
If you're someone who says I'm not going to do that, you are welcome.
You belong.
We love you.
But for those who are going to make decisions, who are going to give us direction,
who are going to help us figure out who our leaders are, and we'll help calling us to,
it's important that you're able to say, "Yep, we're going to do it based on word of God."
And I might disagree with you, and you might disagree with me, and Ryan might disagree with Corey,
and Corey might disagree with me, and that's okay.
But when we have those conversations, we go back to what is the Bible study?
How is the Bible leading us?
Where are you getting that from me?
Right, folks?
We're going to end.